Guide to the Yale College Records Concerning the Education of Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yale College records concerning the education of women
1968-1987
RU 578
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.25
(27 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, committee minutes, and reports documenting the activities of Judith Brandenberg, associate dean of Yale College, concerning the education of women.
Yale College (1887- )
Brandenberg, Judith
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 9-E (YRG 9-E), Records documenting Yale College offices, programs, and projects.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, committee minutes, and reports documenting the activities of Judith Brandenberg, associate dean of Yale College, concerning the education of women.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Coeducation; Women college students; Women -- Education; Yale College (1887- ); Yale University -- Students
- Records concerning the education of women, 1968-1985; Accession 1988-A-009
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2021.
  - Admissions information, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Committee on the Education of Women: Minutes and Material, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Affirmative Action, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Affirmative Action and Coeducation: Research and Articles, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 7)
  - Alumnae lists, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Survey, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9 - 11)
  - Annual Report, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Articles on women in Education, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Athletics
    - Report of Yale Commission, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15 - 16)
    - Women at Yale: Post Coeducation, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Career Choice, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Center For Independent Study, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Charts (color), for the Vassar-Yale (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Study Group: Preliminary Report, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Committee on
    - Academic Development, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Coeducation, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Education of women, 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 26)
      Scope and Contents
      Contains records on an open house for "Women in Science and Math".
    - The Status of Professional Women at Yale, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27 - 29)
  - Conference mailing list, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Day care and education of children, 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Faculty and Professioanl Women's Forum, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Faculty Women/Tenure, 1974-1981 (Box 3, Folder 33 - 35)
  - Fellowship information, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Feminist organizations, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Grant and funding information, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Grant proposals, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Henry Fellowship, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Information and Counseling Services for Women, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Job hunting, information on, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Lee, Elizabeth Briant Award, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Medical Academia, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Mentor Program: mailing list, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Minority Statistics and Reports, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Minority Women and Professional Work, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities: Support for Women's Studies, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 49 - 50)
  - "Notable Women at Yale, 1701-1981" Project report (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Off-campus women and statistics, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Office Events, Summary of, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Office for the Education of Women: final report, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Office report, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Older students: mailing lists and correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Onat, Etta S.: Gladly would She Learn and Gladly Teach, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Peters, Ellen Ash, biography of first woman full professor at Yale Law School, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Prizes, 1967-1984 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Project on the Status and Education of Women (Bernice Sandler), 1981 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Questionnaire to Women, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 61 - 62)
  - Race Relations at Yale, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Radcliffe Institute, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - "Rethinking the Education of Women": Conference, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Science C1001X: Syllabus, reading lists and assignments, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Science Conference Report, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Security
    - General information, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Helen Hadley Hall, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Committee, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 70 - 72)
    - Week: final report and publicity, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 73 - 74)
    - Whistlestop Program, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Senior Profile Study: Class of 1980 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Speakers, 1975-1981 (Box 7, Folder 77 - 83)
  - Statistics report, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Status of Professional Women at Yale: report, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Teacher Evaluation, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Title IX (Laws passed against sexual discrimination in Higher Education), work notes, 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 88 - 91)
  - "Transitional" older students (non-Yale), 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 92 - 93)
  - "Transitional" older students (Yale), 1971-1977 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Undergraduate
    - Admissions, 1971-1977 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Women's Caucus, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Women Athletes, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Weekly Bulletin and Calendar, 1979-1984 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Who's Who of American Women (Yale listings), 1981 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Women
    - Administrators meeting, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Affiliated with Yale (W.A.Y.), 1979 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - at other schools, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - and Health, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - in Education: Research and Reports, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - in Higher Education: Institution for (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - for University Women at Yale, 1968-1974 (Box 10)
    - in Mathematics at Yale, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Science and Mathematics
    - Articles by Grace Hopper, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Directory of Yale College, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Glanville, Evelyn Boyd, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Mailing list, Departmental, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Social Sciences (Anne Smith), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Workshop (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Work Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Yale
    - 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Information from Representatives, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 116 - 117)
    - Time Line, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Women's
    - Advisory Council, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - Issues and Careers, 1968-1977 (Box 12, Folder 120 - 127)
    - Liason Committee Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Women's Studies
    - Articles on file, 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 129 - 130)
    - Background information (Box 12, Folder 131 - 133)
    - Core Faculty Meeting, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - Council, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 135)
    - Courses, 1972-1976 (Box 12, Folder 136 - 138)
    - Library Resources, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 139)
    - Office space assignation, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Education Research, 1971-1976 (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Other Institutions, 1970's (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - Women's Week, 1983 April (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - Women's Work (History, Statistics), 1974 (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Work in progress, undated (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Yale
    - Information: Feminist organizations, 1974-1982 (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Institute for Independent Research: proposal, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Yale Women's Forum
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Annual Meeting, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - "Maintaining the Balance": Panel on Personal/Professional Life, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 150)
    - "Women and Economics", 1976 (Box 13, Folder 151)
    - Women's Week, 1976 October (Box 13, Folder 152)
    - Women's Work Program, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 153)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets
      - Statements 990G-0001 and 990G-32-1976907, 1975-1979 (Box 14, Folder 154 - 160)
      - Receipts, 1978 August-December (Box 14, Folder 161 - 164)
      - Receipts, 1979 January-May (Box 15, Folder 165 - 169)
  - Asian-American Students Association: Budget sheets, order forms, receipts, payment requests, 1975-1981 (Box 15, Folder 170 - 172)
  - Education of Women: Special use account, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 173)
  - Gersick-NSF Grant statements, 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 174)
  - Security Project, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 178)
  - Security Week expenses and budget, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 179)
  - Women's Center at Yale: petitions, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 180)
- Records concerning the education of women, 1968-1987; Accession 1988-A-074
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2023.
  - Teaching Fellows
    - Enrollments, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Information, general, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Performance and Supervision, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - PEW 990A, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Proposals: Graduate School, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Provosts' Authorization Letters, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
    - Summary of Expenditures, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Teaching Assistant Letters and Work Letters, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Teaching Fellow
      - Meeting, 1982 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Part-time Acting Instructors, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 14)
      - Record, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15 - 18)
    - Budget
      - 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 21)
      - Committee Meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Contingency Fund
        - Budget, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - General Appropriation, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - Pending Requests, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
        - Transfer Letters, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Decisions, Teaching Fellows, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 27 - 28)
      - Graduate Student Teaching, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Guidelines for the Preparation of Budgets for Teaching by Graduate Students, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 30 - 31)
      - Long, Charles: general information, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Preparation, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 33 - 35)
      - Preparation: Working Copy, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Judith Berman Brandenberg (Box 3)
      - Projections, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Sheets, Budget (Acct #672A), 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Summaries, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Teaching, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Minutes
    - Advisory Committee, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Committee on the Education of Women, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - University Committee minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 43 - 45)
    - Yale Affirmative Action Plan, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 46 - 47)
  - News clippings
    - 1968-1978 (Box 5, Folder 48 - 51)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 52 - 53)
  - Statistics
    - 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 54 - 57)
  - Budgets
    - ACCT # 990G-32-0000, 1979-1982 (Box 8, Folder 58 - 63)
    - ACCT # 990G-32-00001, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 64)
- Records of Judith Brandenberg, 1978-1985; Accession 1989-A-030
  - Council on 3rd World Women, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Comm. Women's Task Force on Mental Health, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Consumer Advisory Committee of the Yale Health Plan, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Consumer Advisory Committee of the Yale Health Plan, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ad. Hoc. Committee on Student Life, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Education of Women, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee on the Education of Women
    - Pre 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Spring 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Handouts, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - MTG Folder, Simmonds Chair, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Membership, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - MTG Folder, Simmonds Chair, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Membership, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Work Force Analysis (Affirmative Action Office), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Sources, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - FASACEW, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty of Arts and Sciences Advisory Committee on the Education of Women, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - FASACEW, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Request for Crothers Report, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters Regarding Crothers Report, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Faculty of Arts and Sciences Advisory Committee on the Education of Women, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Report of the FASACEW, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Duplicates: FASACEW Materials, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Handouts for FASACEW, 10/31/1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - FAS Advisory Committee on the Education of Women
    - Second Meeting, 1983 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Third Meeting, 1983 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fourth Meeting, 1983 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Drafts - FASACEW, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Catering Services (Dining Halls), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Career Counseling for Spouses, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Academic Counseling Tutoring, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Buckley Show, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bachelor of Liberal Studies (BLS), 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Aurelian Honor Society SSS405, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Association of Yale Alumni (AYA)
    - AYA, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - AYA, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Committee on Women, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - AYA, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Committee on Women, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - ACNE Conference, 1982 November 9-10 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Afro-American Cultural Center, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Women and Yale: Transitions Conference/General Information, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Women's Studies Conference University of Kansas, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Women and Yale: Transit Conference becomes a suggestion, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Conference (Women and Yale: Transitions), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Conference News Clippings, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Conference/ Evaluations Forms and lists on names, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - VITA, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Conference-Correspondence (Women and Yale: Transitions), 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Transitions Conference: Student participants and facilitators, 1979 September (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Transitions Conference: Form Letters, 1979 September (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Conference-Brochure Material (Women and Yale: Transitions), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Conference-Budgetory Items 990G 32 87178, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Transfer Housing, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Misc. Tranfer Students, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Transfer Students, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Transfer Admissions, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Transfer Students, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Transfer Admissions
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 1976 Jun (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Transfer Students
    - 1977 Jan (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - 1977 Jun (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - 1978 Jan (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - 1978 Jun (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - 1979 Jan (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - 1979 Jun (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Dean's Advisory Committee on Grievance Procedures, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Grievance Board
    - Nominees, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Sexual Harassment Origins, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Pamphlet Draft, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - General, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Grievance Board Newsclippings, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Dean's Advisory Committee on Student Grievances, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Grievance Board--Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Provost Grievance Procedure and College Stud. Comp. Proc., 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Grievance Board--Procedures Report, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Grievance Board, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Grievance Board--Handouts, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Grievance/Request for Information, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Undergraduate Regulations (Sexual Harassment), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Grievance Board
    - Student Complaints of Sexual Harassment, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Rev Proc Faculty Mtg., 1980 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Grievance Board-Sexual Harassment, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Grievance Board Summary, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Yale College Dean's Office
    - to 1980 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Dean Lamar, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Yale College Calendar, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - YCDO-Annual Report T of V 79-1982 Lamar, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - YCDO, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Subsidies and Honoraries
    - 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Organization of Concern to Women Around New Haven, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 108)